(IF I HAD A HEART PLAYING)
Tell me what
it is you want.
Are you unhappy?
Do you think the gods
have cheated you?
I want my old
position back.
I was never meant
to be a servant,
a slave, a friend.
I am bitter
and I am angry.
Everything I had,
everything I possessed,
everything that
I was,
has been stripped
away from me.
And my anger is
like a stone...
A stone that I carry
inside me that...
Weighs me down.
I cannot lift it.
In some ways,
you are still fortunate.
Ragnar could
have had you killed,
at the same time
as your husband.
I am supposed to be
eternally grateful,
to my husband's killer?
I ask you once more,
why you have come here,
if you do not think, I can
offer you any comfort.
I want to know,
will the gods ever
smile on me again?
The gods will always
smile on brave women,
like the Valkyries,
those furies who
men fear and desire.
(INDISTINCT CHATTER)
You'll have to forgive
the poverty of the feast.
It has been a hard winter.
We had to burn
our own grain stores,
to rid ourselves
of Jarl Borg.
So I heard.
Tell us, Erlendur,
what happened in
England after we left?
We were betrayed
by King Ecbert.
We made contact, and
your Christian friend
Athelstan, arranged for
further talks, or so he said.
In retrospect, I wonder
who's side he was really on.
In any case,
the trickster was at work.
Ecbert never meant to
honor his promises to you.
We were betrayed,
taken by surprise.
There was
a great slaughter.
Erlendur and I barely
escaped with our lives.
What about Athelstan?
Where is he now?
If he is fortunate,
he died in battle.
In any case,
let's not speak of him.
He was a
worthless individual.
Poor Athelstan.
My sister and I grew
to love him, when
we were children.
FLOKI: He fooled you,
young Bjorn.
He never denounced his
Christian God.
He was our enemy.
We should rejoice
at his death.
So...
What do you intend
on doing now?
What do you think, Ragnar?
I intend on gaining
revenge on King Ecbert.
We should plan a raid
as soon as possible.
ROLLO: I would be very
happy to take part in it.
King Ecbert should
certainly be punished.
I agree.
We should return
to Wessex.
But first,
Jarl Borg must
pay the price,
for what he did
to my family,
and to our people.
(GASPS)
Forgive me, master.
No, it doesn't matter.
HORIK: I understand,
completely,
and if I were you,
I would feel the same way.
But we must
remember our agreement
and what it was for.
We would sail west to
raid and to colonize.
That was your dream, Ragnar,
and I have come
to share it.
But now, we have neither
the men nor the ships,
to realize our dreams.
What are you saying?
I think we should
go back to Jarl Borg.
He is licking his wounds.
He is no longer as
strong as he was.
And, yet, we need him.
We cannot go west
without his ships.
And so, once again,
we should ask him
to join our alliance.
Don't listen to him.
But who should
go to Jarl Borg?
I think it should
be you, Rollo.
After all, you know
him better than anyone.
What do you think?
Farewell, my love.
I will pray to Thor
that he grant
you safe passage.
MAN: Throw that.
May you have success, Rollo,
for the sake of all of us.
MAN: Man your stations.
MAN 2: Stores aboard.
MAN 3: All the men aboard!
Rollo.
MAN: Try the sail then.
I, too, wish you well.
Those words mean
a lot coming from you.
They were hard to say.
Now they are said.
Cast away!
MAN: Ready the oars!
It has an unusual
taste, wine.
But then, you're
an unusual woman, Siggy.
You don't like wine?
(SPITS)
It's horrible.
The finer things in life
are an acquired taste.
I hope you do not
mind I brought my
son with me?
I want him to start to
understand the game.
The game?
The game you and I play.
The game Ragnar
tries to play.
Are you sure
it is a game?
Why do you invite
me to your bed?
Why do you tell me
things about Ragnar?
Everything I do,
I do for Rollo.
And not for yourself?
If Rollo rises,
I rise also.
And you need my help.
(CHUCKLING)
Well, what do you think,
King Horik?
And what would you do,
Siggy,
for my continued
and active support?
(LAUGHING)
My son is ignorant
of the game,
and strangely ignorant
of other things as well.
(CHUCKLES)
He's only been
with a few women,
and they were nothing...
Slaves, girls.
I want him to
enjoy the attentions
of an experienced,
free woman.
(EXHALING)
Erlendur, come.
SIGVARD:  She sees a hall
more fair than the sun,
thatched with gold, at Gimle.
There shall the gods
in innocence dwell,
and live forever
a life of bliss.
(BURPING)
Why don't we have poets
here anymore?
Poets to entertain us.
Sing to us.
Make us laugh.
I remember when
this great hall,
was always full of laughter.
Laughter and good
fellowship.
WOMAN: You can see
it in her eyes.
My wife has
returned to me.
(CHUCKLING)
That's good.
(SCATTERED LAUGHTER)
She went without
my permission.
But, as you can all see,
she has come back,
and I love her for it.
After all, what man
wouldn't be pleased,
at the return
of such a wife?
Skal.
ALL:  Skal!
Skal, husband.
Unfortunately,
you left my
stepson behind.
MAN: It's time to leave.
Gerta, take my hand.
Come. Come.
He wanted to stay
with his father.
He's old enough to decide.
Is it not enough
that I came back?
No, it's not enough,
my dear wife,
it's... It's not enough.
Of course it's not enough.
It's an insult to me.
What else could
I have done?
His father is
Ragnar Lothbrok.
(METAL CLATTERING)
Who is this
Ragnar Lothbrok?
Nothing but a windbag,
an opportunist.
A man so bloated
with self-importance,
he pretends to be
descended from Odin!
(ALL LAUGHING)
He doesn't need to
pretend anything.
Now I know for sure why
you went to defend him.
Not to repulse
a foreign invader,
as you lied to me,
but because
you're still in
love with him.
You're still in love
with Ragnar Lothbrok,
aren't you, wife?
You can sleep
alone tonight.
I have made
other arrangements.
(DOOR CREAKING)
(TREMBLING BREATH)
(FOOTSTEPS)
(ALL GRUNTING)
Master, can I help you?
I was going to ask
you the same question.
Those buckets
look very heavy.
I'm used to it.
What is your name?
Porunn.
Sit a moment.
I have to finish my work.
It is all right.
Where do you sleep?
In that barn
with the other
servants and animals.
Do you...
Have a boyfriend?
Of course!
I must finish my work.
ASLAUG: She is
remarkably good looking.
If you say so.
Why do you let Horik
decide everything?
Can you really
forgive Jarl Borg?
Do you know how much I
suffered because of him?
How much your
son suffered?
Yes.
I know.
But you do
nothing about it!
By insulting and
humiliating me,
he insulted and
humiliated you.
My father never would
have allowed such a thing.
He would have
been revenged.
Your father cannot
do too much now,
being dead.
What is wrong?
You are quite safe.
Where is he?
Sit down.
What is that?
The skull of my first wife.
She continues to advise me.
Is that fair to her?
So...
Your brother
wants me to come
and fight for him?
He wants to rebuild
the original alliance
between himself,
King Horik, and you.
He believes that,
in our small countries,
cooperation is
the only way forward.
So, he does not
want revenge upon me?
After all,
I invaded his lands.
Men like you
and I will always
look for revenge.
Ragnar looks beyond.
Then he is a most
extraordinary man indeed.
As forgiving
as a Christian!
He is also
a practical man.
He and King Horik
have lost a lot of men.
They need you to
help them raid.
BORG: What do
you say, my love?
(SNIFFING)
You think I should go?
She thinks I should go.
Torvi, bring some mead.
Yes, Jarl Borg.
You and I must drink, to this
most unexpected,
but not unwelcome event.
My wife will join us.
Pour it in here.
Skal.
You have a great
gift, Athelstan.
I believe it is a...
A divine gift.
Thank you, sire.
I thought I might
have forgotten, but...
I love these materials.
Brushes, the paints,
the colors.
I had not appreciated
how much I missed my work.
The pagans have
nothing like it?
No.
They have no art.
They can neither
read nor write,
except for their
carved runes.
Hmm.
And their gods?
Uh, Odin and Thor
and Freyr.
(CHUCKLING)
How strange you
must have found them.
In some ways, yes.
In other ways...
In other ways?
Their gods are very old.
And sometimes I could
not help noticing,
some similarities
with our own God,
and his son.
For example,
their god, Odin,
whom they call the All-father,
the god of gods,
wanted to discover
what it was like to die.
So, according to their
stories and traditions,
Odin hung himself
from a tree,
and a pagan servant,
stabbed him in his side
with a spear,
just like the Romans
did to Christ.
Come with me.
Tell me honestly.
What do you
think of these works?
I find them
indescribably
beautiful.
But they are
clearly pagan.
(CHUCKLING)
You are only a monk,
Athelstan, and yet,
somehow, I...
I begin to trust you.
I feel you...
You are a kindred spirit.
Who?
Who painted these images?
What race of man
was ever so glorious,
that they filled
our world with such,
as you say,
indescribable beauty?
I have been told, sire,
that you served at the court,
of the emperor Charlemagne,
which I have
also visited.
I cannot imagine,
therefore, that you
do not know what I know.
That these images were
painted by the Romans.
They conquered these
lands a long time ago.
They conquered
the whole world.
But they were pagans.
They worshipped false gods.
Never speak of
our conversation
to any other man here.
Nobody else would
understand it.
They would fear it.
(LAUGHING)
They accept
an interpretation,
that a race of giants
once lived here.
(LAUGHING)
And that we have
nothing to do with them.
(CHUCKLES)
The fact is, Athelstan,
we have lost more
knowledge than we
ever had!
These Romans knew things
that we will never know!
Their pagan gods allowed
them to rule the world.
And what is the
lesson that we can
learn from that?
(MUSIC PLAYING)
(MUSIC STOPS)
What do you want,
master?
Forgive me.
I just came to listen.
You won't like
our music.
It's rough.
I would still like
to stay.
That is,
if you allow it.
(MUSIC PLAYING)
(TREMBLING BREATHING)
AETHELWULF: Monk.
(GASPS)
My father desires
to see you.
Father's waiting for you
behind this door.
Come and see.
Look around.
You thought those
paintings were all
that there was.
But of all Roman
things, these are
the most precious.
Tales of the Caesars.
The fall and ruin
of Roman Britain.
Tales of emperors
and empires...
It's the stuff of
dreams, Athelstan.
It's the very
fabric of dreams.
You can read them,
of course.
Yes. Yes, I can
read them.
Good.
That is why
I've chosen you.
What do you mean?
Well, I've chosen you
to be the guardian, of
these books
and their secrets.
I want you to copy them.
You speak Latin,
not many do.
Your job will be to
preserve these works
and these...
Fragments,
for all eternity.
But if you ever tell
anyone about them,
I will let them
crucify you.
I hope you were telling
me the truth, Rollo.
Why don't you ask her?
(INDISTINCT CONVERSATIONS)
Jarl Borg.
Please.
Earl Ragnar Lothbrok,
can I say,
in all honesty,
you're a greater
man than I am.
I know, I don't deserve
the chance, you have given me,
to raid and work with you,
but I swear on my ring,
from henceforth,
you've no reason
to doubt my loyalty,
or my commitment
to our common cause.
If we are being honest,
I can tell you that
it was King Horik,
who argued for
a renewal of our
alliance.
As you can imagine,
I was not, at first,
enthusiastic.
But then...
Then I realized
what could be
gained by inviting you.
We have much to gain
if we work together,
and a lot to
lose if we don't.
Even I can see that now.
(CHUCKLES)
(LAUGHING)
Torstein.
Yes, My Lord.
Put Jarl Borg's men
in the barn which
the servants use.
And treat them
with respect.
Of course, My Lord.
Thank you.
HORIK: Siggy.
I never once for a moment
imagined, Ragnar
would take my advice,
and invite Jarl Borg,
to rejoin our alliance.
As I told you,
Ragnar is different.
Whatever you think
he will do,
he will always
do the opposite.
And I wanted to thank you
for what you did
for my son.
You made him a man.
Do not ask me to do
it for your other sons.
I am not a whore.
No. Just for me.
Can you keep a secret?
(CHUCKLING) No.
(MUSIC PLAYING)
(SIGHING)
What's the matter
with you, my love?
You don't talk,
you don't smile.
My love, you must
do better than this.
You know something?
My wife has
got the most
beautiful breasts.
I keep telling her,
but she doesn't
believe me.
She has the most
beautiful breasts
in the world.
(INDISTINCT MURMURING)
They're like
Freya's breasts.
The breasts of a goddess.
Let me show you.
(ALL GASP)
(SCREAMING)
(HUSHED CHATTERING)
ASLAUG: The giant king's
servants,
carried a trencher
into the hall,
and set it down
before the throne.
They heaped it with
hunks of chopped meat,
and it reminded Thor,
that rather too
long had gone, by
since they had last eaten.
Thor was so hungry!
A chair was provided
for Loki, at one end
of the trencher,
and for Logi at the other.
(EAGLE CALLING)
ASLAUG:  At the word from
the giant king,
they both began to eat.
They gobbled and
consumed and...
(BOTH GIGGLING)
Each of them ate as
fast as they could,
edging their chair forward,
and they met at
the middle of the trencher.
Loki had eaten
every scrap of meat,
and left nothing
but the bones.
(BREATHING HEAVILY)
Where are you going?
But Logi had not
only eaten the meat,
he had eaten the bones
and the trencher as well.
I think Logi won.
(GRUNTING)
(WATER DRIPPING)
(FOOTSTEPS)
Who is it?
SEER: Yes, I can see,
and I see an eagle.
I see that an eagle
hovers over you.
But I also see
that you yourself
are the eagle.
ASLAUG:  "I would say,"
proclaimed the giant king,
"that Loki is the loser."
(WHISPERING) Hush, Ubbe.
Hvitserk is nearly asleep.
Now you go to sleep.
I don't want to.
Why not?
Because whenever you dream,
you never know what
is going to happen.
(MEN GROANING)
MAN: What's happening?
What?
All you folk in the barn.
If you want to live,
stay silent.
Nothing will happen to you.
ALL: No!
No! Fire!
(MEN SHOUTING)
WOMAN: Let us out!
WOMAN 2: Let us out!
ROLLO: Where have you been?
Here and there.
Up and down.
Where is Bjorn?
He is supposed
to be with you.
I don't know, Rollo.
Let's go.
It is fine, come.
You can sleep here.
No, I can't.
Of course you can.
Why not?
This is your place.
I cannot sleep here.
Well, don't you want to?
What does it matter
what I want to do?
Well, what if
I ordered you
to stay here?
Then I would have to
heed your command.
I don't want to order you.
I want you to
choose to stay here.
Is this what
you want?
Master?
Good evening, Jarl Borg.
(GRUNTING)
(SIGHING)
I told you...
I always look for revenge.
(GROANING)
(GRUNTING)
No!
(GASPS)
(MUFFLED GRUNT)
Not necessary.
(GRUNTING)
(ROARING)
What is all the commotion?
LOTHBROK: I am sorry,
that the ambiance
of Kattegat,
has awoken you.
What is the cause of this?
MAN: In here!
HORIK: Is he dead?
FLOKI: No, no, no.
FLOKI: He's not dead.
Yet.
(GRUNTING)
Why have you done this?
Did you really think,
that I could ever
forgive this man,
for threatening
to kill my family?
So, what will you do now?
Since you consort
with eagles,
I will draw a blood eagle
on your back.
No.
And your ribcage
will spring apart.
No.
Yes.
Like wings.